Guide to the Clarke & Rapuano Landscape Architecture Collection 1935–2002 (bulk, 1935–1975) PR 080
New-York Historical Society
Clarke & Rapuano landscape architecture collection
1935–2002 (bulk, 1935–1975)
New-York Historical Society
Clarke & Rapuano
PR 080
5.29 Linear feet in 7 boxes.
Collection of black and white photographs and photonegatives taken by the urban redevelopment firm of Clarke & Rapuano, representing many of their projects in New York City, with the earliest images dating to the 1930s. Includes cityscapes, aerial views, and photographs of architectural models and designs. Projects include the Metropolitan Life Insurance Company's housing developments at Stuyvesant Town, Peter Cooper Village, and Parkchester. Numerous ground and aerial views show the Brooklyn Heights Esplanade over the Brooklyn-Queens Expressway. Other projects represented include buildings for the New York World's Fair in 1939 and 1964, restoration of Bryant Park, Central Park Zoo and Conservatory, JFK International Airport, Queens Zoo, the Van Wyck Expressway, Henry Hudson Parkway, Major Deegan Expressway, and Washington Square in Greenwich Village. Additional materials include printed material documenting several urban redevelopment projects carried out by the firm, and reports for projects on which Clarke or Rapuano were consulted by city agencies.
Arrangement
The collection is organized in two series:
Series I.
Project File Photographs, 1935–1986, undated
Series II.
Print Matter, 1940–2002
Biographical / Historical
Gilmore D. Clarke (1892–1982) and Michael Rapuano (1904–1975) began a professional partnership in Engineering and Landscape Architecture in 1934. Both men were trained at Cornell, and Clarke was later a professor of architecture there, as well as Dean of Cornell's College of Architecture. Their first collaboration was on the design of the Henry Hudson Parkway, and the success of that project encouraged the two to become one of the first multi-discipline firms in the country, with a staff of landscape architects, architects, engineers, and planners. From 1944 to 1954 the practice included Leslie G. Holleran as a principal and named partner.
The firm of Clarke & Rapuano seems to have its hand in most of the major building projects in New York City between 1935 and 1965. Clarke served on the Board of Directors for the 1939–1940 World's Fair, and was a consultant to the Board for the subsequent 1964–1965 Fair. Many private exhibits at the 1939 Fair used Clarke & Rapuano as their landscape architects. Both Clarke & Rapuano were on the Board of Design for Metropolitan Life's four major housing projects: Stuyvesant Town, Peter Cooper Village, Riverton and Parkchester. The firm was appointed to be the landscape architects as well as site-engineers for all four projects. The firm also prepared plans for the development of the grounds of the United Nations; Clarke was on the board of Consulting Architects-Engineers for that project.
While Gilmore Clarke seemed to specialize in planning and design, Michael Rapuano often focused on roadways and their implementation and inclusion in the existing landscape. He served on several local and national committees to study the freeway systems that were becoming more important in the 1940s and 1950s. Clarke & Rapuano worked on several of Robert Moses' major projects: The Major Deegan Expressway in the Bronx, the Van Wyck Expressway in Queens, and the Brooklyn-Queens Expressway, including the design of the Brooklyn Heights Esplanade, built over part of that highway.
In 1975 the founding partners both retired, and the firm was bought by the remaining principals, and continued to do the same kind of planning and landscape design work until 1998.
Access Restrictions
Open to qualified researchers by appointment only. To schedule an appointment, contact the Print Room Librarian at printroom@nyhistory.org.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Domenico Annese, 1999, 2002.
Related Materials
Other aerial photographs of large housing projects can be found in the Thomas Airviews Collection (PR 106). Other material on the New York World's Fairs can be found throughout the Department of Prints, Photographs, and Architectural Collections, particularly in the Album File (PR 002) and in the Geographic Images Collection (PR 020).
Scope and Contents
The Clarke & Rapuano Landscape Architecture Collection spans the period from 1935 to 2002 and primarily contains photographs relating to urban redevelopment projects carried out, mainly in New York City, by the firm between 1939 and 1970. The collection includes photographs, negatives, and printed and published materials documenting the New York World's Fairs (both 1939–1940 and 1964–1965), restoration of public parks, John F. Kennedy (formerly Idlewild) International Airport, public housing projects as well as those built by Metropolitan Life, planning and construction of several major highways in the region, and a few mid-century modern skyscrapers.
This collection does not include any architectural drawings, plans, or models. A few photographs show plans or renderings for projects, but most images show the final result of projects. Domenico Annese, donor of the collection, joined the firm of Clarke & Rapuano in 1956, became its Executive Vice President in 1975, and continued to work as a consultant after his retirement in 1991. In the process of gathering his files and organizing them for donation, he made notations on prints and negative sleeves that are helpful in the identification of many projects.
The collection is divided in two series: Series I. Project File Photographs, and Series II. Print Matter.
Series I. Project File Photographs includes photographic material documenting many of the firm's projects. While the firm was involved in projects throughout the eastern United States, the vast majority of the projects represented here were in New York City. Most of the public works projects included in the collection were commissioned by the New York City Department of Parks, the New York City Planning Commission, the New York City Airport Authority, and the New York State Department of Public Works, among other government commissions and bodies.
Series I encompasses two basic formats: photographic prints (including snapshots, aerial views, contract photos, and contact sheets) and negatives (safety acetate film versions of most of the prints). The prints generally show projects in a state of completion, but some project files include photographs of renderings or presentation drawings. These have been noted in the container list when they are present. Aerial photographs in the collection were taken by McLaughlin Aerial Surveys, Aero Services, Thomas Airviews, and Skyviews. Most photographs from the 1930s through 1950s were taken by John Gass. Other photographers represented in the collection are David Plowden, Gottscho-Schleisner, and members of the Clarke & Rapuano firm. Some projects are represented solely by negatives, such as many of the New York City housing projects, as well as some New York City park projects. The negatives of the Astoria Park are primarily focused on the large pool in that park.
Series II. Print Matter includes company promotional materials and various printed reports for projects on which the firm or the principals were involved. Materials about the firm include several company histories prepared by Domenico Annese, Photographs of Clarke & Rapuano, from circa 1968, a detailed listing of the firm's projects from the late 1950s, and material from a 1970 exhibit for the American Society of Landscape Architects. Printed reports involve the following projects: John F. Kennedy (formerly Idlewild) International Airport, New York World's Fair 1964–1965, and several reports on traffic congestion and freeways in urban areas. Each report is entered individually in the container list.
Aerial photographs.; Architectural drawings (visual works); negatives (photographs); Photographic prints.; Presentation drawings (proposals); Brooklyn Heights (New York, N.Y.); Henry Hudson Parkway (New York, N.Y.); Parkchester (New York, N.Y.); Pelham Bay Park (New York, N.Y.); City planners.; City planning -- New York (State) -- New York.; Landscape architects.; Parks -- New York (State) -- New York.; Urban landscape architecture -- Designs and plans.; Urban landscape architecture -- New York (State) -- New York.; Urban renewal -- New York (State) -- New York.; Clarke, Gilmore D., 1892-1982; Rapuano, Michael; American Society of Landscape Architects. New York Chapter; Clarke & Rapuano; Clarke, Rapuano & Holleran; Metropolitan Life Insurance Company; New York (N.Y.). Department of Parks; New York World's Fair (1939-1940: New York, N.Y.) [111] -- Photographs.; New York World's Fair (1964-1965: New York, N.Y.) [111] -- Photographs.
- Series I. Project File Photographs, 1935–1986, undated
  - Astoria Park — negatives, 1937–1939 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Battery Park — prints, 1940–1957 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Battery Park — prints, oversize (3), 1940-1941 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Battery Park — negatives, circa 1939, 1940 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Battery Park — negatives, oversize (1), undated (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Belmont Park Race Track — negatives, undated (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Brooklyn Heights Esplanade and Brooklyn Queens Expressway — prints, 1957–1967 (Box 1, Folder 2-3)
    Scope and Contents
    Includes photos of drawings of Esplanade railings.
  - Brooklyn Heights Esplanade and Brooklyn Queens Expressway — prints, oversize (2), circa 1967 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Brooklyn Heights Esplanade and Brooklyn Queens Expressway — negatives, 1967, undated (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Bryant Park — prints, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Bryant Park — prints, oversize (5), undated (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Bryant Park — negatives, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Bucks County Bridge Design — prints, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Photos of presentation drawings.
  - Cadman Plaza, Civic Center, Brooklyn — negatives, undated (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Central Park. Conservatory Gardens — prints, 1937–1939, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Central Park. Conservatory Gardens — negatives, 1937–1939, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 30–31)
    Includes slides.
  - Central Park. Simon Bolivar Monument — negatives, undated (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Central Park. Zoo (at the Arsenal) — negatives, 1939 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Central Park. Plan for Development of the Lower Reservoir Site, Central Park, 1930 (Box 5, Folder 73–74)
    Print and negatives of presentation drawing, titled above.
  - Claremont Park, Bronx — negatives, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 34)
    Includes slide.
  - Cypress Hills Houses — negatives, undated (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Eastchester Houses — prints, circa 1962 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Eastchester Houses — negatives, circa 1962 (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Fort Tryon Park — negatives, 1936–1938 (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Harlem River Houses — negatives, undated (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Henry Hudson Parkway — prints, 1947–1973 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Henry Hudson Parkway — prints, oversize (1), undated (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Henry Hudson Parkway — negatives, 1935, circa 1947 (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - John F. Kennedy International Airport — prints, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - John F. Kennedy International Airport — prints, oversize (2), undated (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - John F. Kennedy International Airport — negatives, circa 1960 (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - Lever House — prints, circa 1960 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Lever House — negatives, circa 1960 (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - Major Deegan Expressway, Bronx — prints, 1952–1957 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    Includes photos of presentation drawings.
  - Major Deegan Expressway, Bronx — negatives, 1952–1967 (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - Major Deegan Expressway, Bronx — lantern slides (12), [undated?] (Box 4)
  - New York World's Fair (1939–1940). Ford Motor Company Pavilion — prints (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - New York World's Fair (1939–1940). Ford Motor Company Pavilion — negatives (Box 2, Folder 43)
  - New York World's Fair (1939–1940). R.C.A. Pavilion — negatives (Box 2, Folder 44)
  - New York World's Fair (1939–1940). Temple of Religion — prints (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - New York World's Fair (1939–1940). Temple of Religion — negatives (Box 2, Folder 45)
  - New York World's Fair (1939–1940). Trylon / Perisphere — prints (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - New York World's Fair (1939–1940). Trylon / Perisphere — negatives (Box 2, Folder 46)
  - New York World's Fair (1939–1940). General views — prints (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - New York World's Fair (1964–1965) — prints (Box 1, Folder 16)
    Includes photo of rendering of Unisphere.
  - New York World's Fair (1964–1965) — prints, oversize (3), undated (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - New York World's Fair (1964–1965) — negatives (Box 2, Folder 47)
  - Orchard Beach, Pelham Bay Park — prints, circa 1936 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Orchard Beach, Pelham Bay Park — negatives, 1936 (Box 2, Folder 48)
  - Parkchester Houses — prints, 1941, circa 1952 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Parkchester Houses — prints, oversize (5), undated (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Parkchester Houses — negatives, circa 1940 (Box 2, Folder 49)
  - Pelham Parkway Houses — prints, circa 1962 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Pelham Parkway Houses — negatives, circa 1962 (Box 2, Folder 50)
  - Peter Cooper Village — negatives, undated (Box 2, Folder 51)
  - Playland, Rye Beach — negatives, undated (Box 2, Folder 52)
  - Polo Grounds Houses — negatives, undated (Box 2, Folder 53)
  - Queens Zoo, Flushing Meadows Park — prints, oversize (1), circa 1967 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Queens Zoo, Flushing Meadows Park — negatives, 1971 (Box 2, Folder 54)
  - Rockefeller Center, Roof Gardens — prints, circa 1960 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Rockefeller Center, Roof Gardens — negatives, circa 1960 (Box 3, Folder 55)
  - Samuel J. Tilden Houses — negatives, undated (Box 3, Folder 56)
  - Sara Delano Roosevelt Playground — negatives, 1937–1939 (Box 3, Folder 57)
  - Seagram Building — prints, circa 1960 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Stuyvesant Town — prints, undated (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Stuyvesant Town — negatives, undated (Box 3, Folder 58)
  - Todt Hill Houses — prints, circa 1962 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Todt Hill Houses — negatives, 1962, undated (Box 3, Folder 59)
  - United Nations — negatives, circa 1971 (Box 3, Folder 60)
  - Van Wyck Expressway — negatives, circa 1948–1949 (Box 3, Folder 61)
  - Washington, D.C. East Capitol Street — negatives, undated (Box 3, Folder 62)
  - Washington, D.C. East Capitol Street — oversize / separated, undated (Box 5, Folder 75)
  - Washington, D.C. Klingle Road Bridge, Rock Creek Park — prints, oversize (1), undated (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Washington Square Park — negatives, circa 1960 (Box 3, Folder 63)
  - Westway State Park — negatives, 1985 (Box 3, Folder 64)
- Series II. Print Matter, 1940–2002
  - Promotional Material, circa 1957–2000
    - Clarke & Rapuano promotional brochures and books, 1972–[1988] (Box 3, Folder 65)
    - Clarke & Rapuano company histories, circa 1957–2000 (Box 3, Folder 66)
    - Photographs of Gilmore Clarke and Michael Rapuano, circa 1968 (Box 3, Folder 67)
    - Exhibition Materials, Regional Landscape Architect Meeting, Laconia, N.H., 1970–1971 (Box 3, Folder 68–69)
  - Reports and Publications, 1940–2002
    - Architecture & Design, vol. IV, no. 12, 1940 July (Box 5, Folder 76)
      Issue devoted to the work of Gilmore D. Clarke.
    - Clarke & Rapuano, Andrews & Clarke, Richard C. Guthridge. Preparation of the Site for the World's Fair (New York: Clarke & Rapuano) [2 copies], 1960 (Box 5, Folder 77)
    - Clarke & Rapuano, Andrews & Clarke, Richard C. Guthridge. Preparation of the Site for the World's Fair: Supplementary Report (New York: Clarke & Rapuano), 1960 (Box 5, Folder 77)
    - Clarke & Rapuano, Inc. Grade Separations, 2002 (Box 3, Folder 70)
      Disbound report; prepared by Domenico Annese.
    - Downer, Green and Carillo; Clarke, Rapuano & Holleran; Harrison and Abromovitz. The New York Municipal Airport at Idlewild (New York) [2 copies], 1946 (Box 5, Folder 78)
    - Dunn, Gano, W. Earle Andrews, Gilmore D. Clarke for the Engineering Committee of New York City Traffic. Selected Measures for the Partial Relief of Traffic Congestion in New York City (New York: The Committee), 1946 (Box 6, Folder 79)
    - New York City Department of Parks and the Staten Island Historical Society. Richmondtown Restoration. Staten Island. City of New York (New York), 1956 (Box 3, Folder 71)
    - New York City Mayor's Committee on Plan and Scope. Plan for Permanent World Capitol at Flushing Meadow Park (New York: The Committee), 1946 (Box 6, Folder 80)
      Clarke & Rapuano drafted the plan.
    - New York World's Fair 1964–1965 Corporation. Flushing Meadow and Beyond: Preliminary Report on an Proposed Post World's Fair Program (New York) (Box 6, Folder 81)
      Clarke & Rapuano acted as consultants on this planning project.
    - New York World's Fair 1964–1965 Corporation. Post Fair Plan: Queens Zoological and Botanical Gardens (New York: New York World's Fair 1964–1965 Corporation) (Box 6, Folder 82)
    - Urban Advisors to the Federal Highway Administrator. The Freeway in the City: Principles of Planning and Design. A Report to the Secretary, Department of Transportation (Washington: U.S.G.P.O.), 1968 (Box 3, Folder 72)
      Michael Rapuano was the chair of the Advisory Committee.